中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain
藍光版字幕製作  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第五集
宇宙的年齡和體積
The age and size of the cosmos
由光來書寫
are written in light.
迷人的本質和恆星的物質
The nature of beauty and the substance of the stars,
時空的定律
the laws of space and time...
原本就存在
they were there all along,
但我們過去未能發現
but we never saw them...
直到我們擁有了更為強大的觀察方式
until we devised a more powerful way of seeing.
這種覺醒的故事有很多的開始
The story of this awakening has many beginnings
卻不會終止
and no ending.
從不同時間和地方涌現出許多的英雄
Its heroes come from many times and places--
中國古代的哲人
an Ancient Chinese philosopher,
令11世紀伊拉克穆斯林統治者嘆服的奇才
a wizard who amazed the caliphs of 11th-century Iraq,
被苛刻奴役的德國可憐孤兒
a poor German orphan enslaved to a harsh master.
每一位都帶領我們前進一小步
Each one brought us a little closer
在解開光線之謎的道路上
to unlocking the secrets hidden in light.
大多數的名字都已經被遺忘了
Most of their names are forever lost to us,
但在某處  很久前  某人的匆匆一瞥
but somewhere, long ago, someone glanced up
注意到了光線展示出的神奇
to see light perform one of its magic tricks.
誰知道呢
Who knows?
或許光線的偶然作為
Maybe that quirk of light
為第一位藝術家帶來了靈感
inspired the very first artist.
這些都是怎麼來的
Where did all this come from?
我們是如何從小量聚居的
How did we evolve from small wandering bands
採集者和獵人 進化而來的
of hunters and gatherers living beneath the stars
最後還成為世界文明的締造者
to become the builders of a global civilization?
中間的過程是怎樣的
How did we get from there to here?
沒有統一的答案
There's no one answer.
氣候的變化  學會控制火
Climate change, the domestication of fire,
工具的發明 語言發明 農業發展
the invention of tools,  language, agriculture
都有各自的功勞
all played a role.
或許還有其他的
Maybe there was something else, too.
中國  2000多年前
In China, more than 2,000 years ago,
一位名叫 墨子 的哲人 據說發現了
a philosopher named Mo Tze is said to have observed
光線可以在密閉的寶庫中
that light could be made to paint a picture
即小孔成像
產生圖像
inside a locked treasure room.
這描述的就是第一台照相機
This was the description of the first camera...
暗箱
the camera obscura,
所有成像照相機的原型
the prototype of all image-forming cameras,
包括給你帶來圖像的這台攝像機
including the one that's bringing you this picture.
利用光線這種有趣的現象
Taking advantage of this funny thing that light does
催生了首部的電影
resulted in what could be called the first movie.
墨子 光線大師  專治各種黑暗
Mo Tze, master of light, worked against all forms of darkness.
軍事天才
A military genius
以智抑暴
who only used his talents to prevent violence,
他最著名的成就是
he was legendary for traveling
穿行於戰亂的國家間
among the kingdoms of the warring states,
運用巧妙地策略
employing ingenious strategies
勸導各方休戰
to talk kings out of going to war.
他是兼愛的倡導者
He was one of the first to dream of universal love
提倡消滅統治者帶給人們的
and an end to poverty and other forms of inequality;
貧困與不公
of government for the people...
批判對於宗教和權威的盲從
and to argue against blind obedience to ritual and authority.
在他的著作中  你能發現
In his writings, you can find
科學探索的早期萌芽
early stirrings of the scientific approach.
到墨子那個年代  中國人已經開始
By Mo Tze's time, the Chinese had already been recording
用書籍記錄他們的思想 至少上千年了
their thoughts in books for at least a thousand years.
但我們對他的瞭解 依然僅是隻字片語
Still, our knowledge of him is only fragmentary.
通過許多由他和他的追隨者
It consists largely of the collection of essays
所著的文集而來
attributed to him and his disciples.
其中一篇 題為《非命》
In one of them, entitled "Against Fate,"
故言必有三表
立論一定要有三項標準
a three-pronged test for every doctrine is proposed.
推究來歷
Question its basis--
一、有本之者
是否可以由
ask if it can be verified
普通人的觀感再次驗證的
...by the sights and senses of common people.
二、有原之者
是否可以推廣
ask how it is to be applied
三、有用之者
並使大多數人受益
and if it will benefit the greatest number.
墨子的思想流傳很廣
Mo Tze was extremely popular,
但他身後的數百年
but a few hundred years after his death,
秦始皇  第一位皇帝
Qin Shi Huang, the first emperor,
統一了中國  獨攬大權
and unifier of China, took power.
他將一片大陸變成了一個國家
He took a continent and turned it into a nation
這個現在依然受他影響的國度  中國
that now bears his name... China.
我們大多數人對他的瞭解大多數是
Most of us know Emperor Qin for the army of 7,000
來自守衛陵墓的7000件兵馬俑
terra cotta warriors that guard his tomb.
在秦始皇的領導下
In Emperor Qin's drive
為了鞏固遼闊的帝國
to consolidate his far-flung empire,
他採取極端的手段
he took drastic measures
為所有事物都建立了標準
to standardize everything within it.
包括 鑄造單一貨幣
This included mandating a single coinage,
統一度量衡
making uniform all weights and measures,
車輛與道路的寬度  還有
the widths of carts and roads, as well as the precise way
車同軌
中文書寫形式的規範
the Chinese language was to be written,
書同文
也包括了什麼是可以寫 什麼是可以想的
including what you were allowed to write and think.
秦始皇以嚴刑峻罰來控制臣民思想
使臣民不敢反抗 從而達到順利推行政
秦始皇的哲學 唯一他認可的
Emperor Qin's philosophy-- the only one permitted--
即法家
稱之 守法主義
was called "legalism,"
就如同它的字面意思
which is just what it sounded like,
遵紀守法 否則就...
do as the law says... or else.
這種哲學理論對於質疑權威
It's a philosophy that's not highly conducive
不是十分有利
to questioning authority.
百家思想的書籍
...that all the books of the hundred schools of thought
統統燒掉
shall be be burned,
以古諷今者
that anyone who uses history to criticize the present
全家處斬
shall have his family executed.
墨子和孔子的著作
The works of MoTze and Confucius
還有其他哲人的作品
and other philosophers were destroyed
盡毀於世界歷史上首次的焚書
in the world's first book burning.
數百名書生英勇抵抗
Hundreds of scholars bravely resisted
試圖保護這些禁書
by trying to preserve the forbidden books.
在首都將他們活埋
They were buried alive in the capitol.
咸陽的"焚書坑儒"
科學需要有自由的表達才能繁榮發展
Science needs the light of free expression to flourish.
需要無畏的質疑權威
It depends on the fearless questioning of authority,
開放的交流思想
the open exchange of ideas.
墨子和他的追隨者們所記載的
Sparks of curiosity in the writings of Mo Tze
突發奇想都被抹殺了
and his disciples were effectively stomped out.
影片的再次出現 已是另一個千年之後
It would be another thousand years before the next movie.
幸運的是 我們的想像之舟
Luckily, our Ship of the Imagination
可以帶我們去任何的空間和時間
can take us anywhere in space... and time.
中國和希臘的古人發現
The ancient Chinese and Greeks observed
光線可以展現出各種神奇
that light could be made
但是卻沒人去問
to do wonderful things-- but no one asked that question
小孩子和天才們喜歡問的問題  為什麼
favored by small children and geniuses alike. Why?
直到一千年前
Until a thousand years ago...
伊拉克的巴斯拉城
In the city of Basra, Iraq,
生活著另一位光線大師
there lived another master of light.
海桑極度渴望瞭解自然
Ibn al-Hazen had a passionate desire to understand nature.
他對一切都有疑問
He questioned everything,
特別是那些別人認為理所應當的事情
especially those things that everyone else took for granted.
我們怎麼能看到  他問
"How do we see?" he asked.
有些在他之前的偉大權威
Some of the great authorities who came before him
認為光線從我們的眼中出發
had taught that rays come out of our eyes and travel
在物體上反射 然後返回我們的眼中
to the objects we see before returning to our eyes.
但海桑不認同 理由是恆星離我們那麼遠
But al-Hazen reasoned that the stars were too far distant
什麼東西可以從我們眼中射向星星
for something in our eyes to travel all the way to them
並在一眨眼的時間內返回
and back in the blink of an eye.
很有道理  但海桑並未止步
Excellent reasoning, but al-Hazen didn't stop there.
他絞盡腦汁探索大自然的奧秘
He searched for ways to compel nature to divulge her secrets.
當時他的文化對於新的見解與質疑是開放的態度
His culture was open to new ideas and questioning.
那是科學發展的黃金時代
It was the golden age of science
在伊斯蘭世界
in the Islamic world.
伊斯蘭世界從西班牙的科索瓦
One that stretched from Cordoba in Spain
一直延伸到中亞的撒馬爾罕
all the way to Samarkand in Central Asia.
基督教和猶太教的學者被敬為上賓
Christian and Jewish scholars were honored guests
在開羅  巴格達的研究機構
at the research institutes of Baghdad, Cairo,
和其他伊斯蘭世界的中心
and other Islamic capitols.
不同於秦始皇  哈里發們派遣使者
Instead of burning books, the caliphs sent emissaries
哈里發是穆斯林統治者的稱號
在世界各地搜集書籍
around the world in search of books.
哈里發們大量的資助將這些書籍
The caliphs lavishly funded projects to translate, study,
翻譯 研究  並保存  流傳後世
and preserve them for future generations.
多虧了他們的努力  許多古希臘科學家的
Much of the light of Ancient Greek science would have been
成果才得以保存
permanently extinguished without their efforts.
對科學的狂熱在歐洲再次興起
The reawakening to science that took place in Europe,
發生在幾百年後 多虧了伊斯蘭學者和
hundreds of years later, was kindled by a flame
科學家對這些文獻的
that had been long tended
精心呵護
by Islamic scholars and scientists.
阿拉伯人將新思想由印度傳入西方
The Arabs also imported ideas from India to the West,
包括所謂的  阿拉伯數字
including the so-called Arabic numerals
我們至今都在使用
that we all use today,
還有數字0
and the concept of zero...
確實很方便
which comes in handy
特別是當你書寫 幾十億又幾十億時
when you want to write "billions and billions."
阿拉伯天文學十分具有影響力
Arabic astronomy was so influential,
我們至今依然用阿拉伯語名字來稱呼
that we still call most of the bright stars
那些明亮的恆星
by their Arabic names.
代數  算法  煉金術  酒精 這些英語單詞中的 al
And the "al's" in algebra, algorithm, alchemy, and alcohol
證明了阿拉伯語
are just some of the traces left
是科學界的通用語言
from the time when Arabic was the language of science.
11世紀時  海桑準備嘗試
In the 11th century, Ibn al-Hazen set about trying
驗證他關於光和我們如何看見的理論
to test his ideas about light and how we see.
我們設計了一套實驗測定光線如何移動
So we devised an experiment to determine how light moves.
我們在烈日下支起一頂帳篷
We erected a tent in full daylight
將它完全密封 只允許一束光穿過
and sealed it tightly so that only a single ray of light
射入內部的黑暗中
could pierce its inner darkness.
他用他的智慧
With little more than his brains
加上一件筆直的木質工具  尺子
and a straight piece of wood-- a ruler--
海桑完成了一次科學歷史上
al-Hazen had accomplished a great leap forward
偉大的跨越
in the history of science.
他發現光線呈直線運動
He discovered that light moves in straight lines.
這只是開始
But he was just getting started.
海桑總結出成像的關鍵
Al-Hazen figured out that the key to forming any image--
不論 眼睛還是照相機暗箱
whether you're talking about an eye or camera obscura--
都是通過控制光線進入
is a small opening to restrict the light that can enter
黑暗內室的小孔
an otherwise darkened chamber.
光圈將我們週遭繁雜無關的
That aperture excludes the chaos
光線排除在外
of extraneous light rays that surround us.
光圈越小
The smaller the aperture,
進入的光線角度範圍越小
the fewer directions that light can come from.
使圖像更清晰
And that makes the image sharper.
從而不至於讓光線致盲
So instead of being blinded by the light,
我們可以分辨光線呈現的圖像
we can see everything it has to show us.
海桑親自做出了他的暗箱
Al-Hazen made his own camera obscura
令哈里發們贊嘆不已
and dazzled the caliphs.
有效的暗箱需要明亮的光線
A camera obscura works best in bright light.
夜空中的星光對它來說太暗淡了
The stars of the night sky are way too dim for this.
我們需要更大的孔來收集光線
We somehow need a bigger opening to collect light,
同時我們需要保持焦點
but we also need to maintain focus.
望遠鏡從視野的
A telescope collects light
各個角度收集光線
from any spot in its field of view
遍佈整個鏡片或者鏡子
across the entire lens or mirror,
開孔要比照相機暗箱的小孔大許多
an opening much larger than the camera obscura hole.
這是最早的望遠鏡之一
This is one of the first telescopes...
伽利略在1609年使用過的那個
the one that Galileo looked through in 1609.
他用這個掀開了黑夜的厚重幕布
With it, he pulled aside the heavy curtain of night
並且開始發現宇宙
and began to discover the cosmos.
都歸功於鏡片
The lens made it possible
鏡片為望遠鏡提供了比我們眼睛
for a telescope to have a much larger light-collecting area
更大的光線收集區域
than our eyes have.
大桶比小桶可以收集更多的雨水
Big buckets catch more rain than small ones.
現代的望遠鏡擁有更大收集區域
Modern telescopes have larger collecting areas,
高度敏感的探測器
highly sensitive detectors,
並可以長時間鎖定同一目標
and they track the same object for hours at a time
以搜集盡可能多的光線
to accumulate as much of its light as possible.
像哈勃 這樣的太空望遠鏡
Space-based telescopes such as the Hubble,
搜集來自最久遠星系的
have captured light from the most distant
光線
and ancient galaxies,
為我們帶來大量的更清晰的宇宙圖片
giving us vastly clearer pictures of the cosmos.
海桑發現了光線成像的原理
Al-Hazen discovered how images are formed by light,
但這並不是他最最偉大的成就
but that was far from his greatest achievement.
他是有史以來設定
Ibn al-Hazen was the first person ever
科學原則的第一人
to set down the rules of science.
他創造了一套糾錯機制
He created an error-correcting mechanism,
一套系統的 嚴格的
a systematic and relentless way
審查錯誤觀念的機制
to sift out misconceptions in our thinking.
探究真相是困難的
Finding truth is difficult...
探究真相的道路是崎嶇的
and the road to it is rough.
作為追尋真相的人
As seekers after truth,
不輕易下判斷 不輕信古人所云
you will be wise to withhold judgment and not simply put
是十分明智的
your trust in the writings of the ancients.
你必須質疑並且謹慎的驗證這些理論
You must question and critically examine those writings
從各個角度
from every side.
你只能接受論據和實驗的結果
You must submit only to argument and experiment
而不是別人的說法
and not to the sayings of any person.
因為每個人都有弱點
For every human being is vulnerable
沒有人是完美的
to all kinds of imperfection.
作為尋求真相的人
As seekers after truth,
我們必須懷疑並質疑
we must also suspect and question
我們自己的理論  反覆論證
our own ideas as we perform our investigations,
避免陷入偏見與疏忽
to avoid falling into prejudice or careless thinking.
接受這些方針  真相就在眼前
Take this course, and truth will be revealed to you.
這就是科學的方式
This is the method of science.
得益於此 我們的機器人大使可以
So powerful that it's carried our robotic emissaries
航行到太陽系的邊緣乃至無限的宇宙
to the edge of the solar system and beyond.
它擴展了我們的生命長度
It has doubled our lifespan,
將過去的失落世界
made the lost worlds of the past
帶回現在
come alive.
科學使我們可以對遙遠的未來
Science has enabled us to predict events
做出預測
in the distant future...
讓我們可以彼此以光速交流
and to communicate with each other at the speed of light,
就像你我之間  此時此刻
as I am with you, right at this moment.
這種思考的方式帶給我們力量
This way of thinking has given us powers
那種海桑都認為神奇的力量
that al-Hazen himself would have regarded as wizardry.
他將我們帶上這條崎嶇 無盡的道路
But it was he who put us on this rough, endless road.
將我們帶到一個地方
And now it has taken us to a place
在那裏即使光線也被黑暗掩蓋
where even light itself is enshrouded in darkness.
光線有著獨一無二的屬性
Light has properties unlike anything else
以人類存在的領域來說
in the realm of human existence.
比如光的速度
Take the speed of light.
光的基礎微粒  光子
The basic particle of light, the photon,
當它從原子或分子中誕生時
is born traveling at the speed of light
就有光的速度
as it emerges from an atom or a molecule.
也只有這一種速度
A photon never knows any other speed,
我們尚未發現其他任何可以立即
and we've not found another phenomenon that accelerates
從0加速到速度極限的現象
from zero to top speed instantaneously.
沒有別的東西可以移動這麼快
Nothing else could move as fast.
當我們嘗試將其他粒子不斷加速
When we try to accelerate other particles closer and closer
越接近光速  阻力越大
to the speed of light, they resist more and more,
並且越來越重
as though they're getting heavier and heavier.
還沒有任何實驗可以
No experiment yet devised
將粒子將速度到光的速度
has ever made a particle move as fast as light.
哪是什麼
What was that?
你聽了嗎
You hear something?
說到哪了 哦 對了
Where was I? Oh, yeah.
沒有什麼可以像光那樣
I don't know anything else in life that behaves like light.
我無法將它這種與眾不同的屬性
I cannot reconcile its strange properties
與我其他的感官相調諧
with everything else my senses tell me.
我們相信我們的感官勝過
Our urge to trust our senses overpowers
測量儀器對於
what our measuring devices tell us about
實際情況的結果
the actual nature of reality.
我們的感官對於普通尺寸物體的普通速度來說
Our senses work fine for life-size objects
沒有問題
moving at mammal speeds,
但是卻不適用於光速那些神奇的規則
but are ill-adapted for the wonderland laws of lightspeed.
我們甚至不明白為什麼會有宇宙速度極限
We don't even know why there's a cosmic speed limit.
時間在達到光速時靜止
Time stands still when you're traveling at the speed of light.
到底什麼是光
What is light, anyway?
艾薩克·牛頓始終對光非常著迷
Isaac Newton's enduring fascination with light
從他還是個孩子時
began when he was a child...
就在這個房子裏
in this very house.
他在弱冠之年  就是第一位
By the time he was in his 20s, Newton became the first person
破譯彩虹奧秘的人
to decipher the mystery of the rainbow.
牛頓發現有些光  白光
Newton discovered that some light, or white light,
由所有彩虹的顏色混合而成
is a mixture of all the colors of the rainbow.
重大的發現
Major discovery.
他將之稱為 光譜
He named the displays of colors a "spectrum"
來源於拉丁語中的幻影 或者幽靈
from the Latin for "phantom" or "apparition."
牛大師 抱歉打擾了
Begging your pardon, Master Newton,
晚飯再不吃就要壞了
the cook frets that your dinner will spoil, sir.
呀麥蝶 小牛 別把放大鏡放下
No, Isaac, don't put the magnifying glass down!
光裏還有更神奇的東西
Something even more amazing is hidden in the light--
一串密碼  一條通向宇宙的鑰匙
a code, a key to the cosmos.
牛頓錯過了很重要的一項發現
Isaac Newton didn't miss much, but that one was a beaut.
他錯過了那扇通向神秘宇宙的門
He just walked right past the door to a hidden universe;
那扇門直到150年後才再次開啟
a door that would not swing open again for another 150 years.
歸功於另一位科學家
It would fall on another scientist,
1800年 在工作時
working in the year 1800,
無意間發現了
to stumble on a piece of evidence
我們周圍無可見世界的證據
for the unseen worlds that surround us.
晚上  威廉·赫歇爾搜索天空
By night, William Herschel scanned the heavens
使用當時最大的望遠鏡
with the largest telescope of his time.
白天  赫歇爾做實驗
By day, Herschel performed experiments.
根據牛頓的研究結果  已知日光
From Newton's earlier work, it was known that sunlight
由不同顏色的光混合而成
is a blend of different colors.
所有人都知道  在戶外
And everyone knew, just from being outside,
日光帶來熱量
that sunlight carries heat.
威廉赫歇爾不禁疑問
William Herschel asked
哪種顏色的光帶著更多的熱量
whether some colors of light carry more heat than others.
科學天才的天性就是對那些
The nature of scientific genius is to question
我們認為理所當然的事情產生疑問
what the rest of us take for granted...
然後做用實驗證實
and then do the experiment.
赫歇爾放在光照範圍之外的溫度計
The thermometer that Herschel placed outside the spectrum
是他的對照物
was his control.
對照物在實驗中
The control in any experiment
不參加實驗操作
always lacks the factor being tested.
這樣才能知道你的實驗物
That way, you know if what you're testing is
是否真的是對實驗本身產生反應
really the thing responsible for the observation.
在赫歇爾的試驗中
In Herschel's experiment,
驗證的是
the relationship between
顏色和溫度的關係
color and temperature was being tested,
他用一個溫度計做對照
and so his control was a thermometer
放在白紙上
over the part of the white sheet
日光照射之外
that was not illuminated by sunlight at all.
那個聲音又來了
There's that sound again.
到底是什麼
What is that?
紅光比藍光產生更多的熱
Okay, red light is warmer than blue light.
有趣的發現 但還不算驚天動地
Interesting discovery, but not exactly revolutionary.
你的溫度計沒有問題
No, there's nothing wrong with your thermometer.
你只是發現了一種新的光
You've just discovered a new kind of light.
赫歇爾是首位發現在光譜中
Herschel was the first to detect this unseen presence
紅色以外或以下 不可見光的人
lurking just below the red end of the spectrum.
這就是紅外線名字的由來
That's why it came to be called "infrared."
紅外線=infra red
英語的infra在拉丁語中意為 之下
"Infra" is Latin for the word "below."
它不可見
It's invisible.
我們的眼睛對這類光不敏感
Our eyes are not sensitive to this kind of light,
我們的皮膚不同  我們可以感受到熱
but our skin is-- we feel it as heat.
這才是真正的重大發現
Now, that's a really big discovery.
但是光線之中依然隱藏著
But far greater secrets were still hiding
更大的秘密
deep inside the light.
幾乎與威廉赫歇爾在英格蘭
At about the same time that William Herschel
發現紅外線的同時
was discovering infrared light in his parlor in England,
一位名叫約瑟夫·夫瑯和費的孩子
a young boy named Joseph Fraunhofer
從事著乏味的繁重的工作
was trapped in hopeless drudgery.
他站在盛滿有毒化學物的熔爐旁
He stood over a cauldron of toxic chemicals
不斷地攪拌
and endlessly stirred.
約瑟夫11歲時成了孤兒
Joseph had been orphaned at the age of 11
被送給苛刻的維塞伯格
and given to a harsh master named Weichselberger,
他替皇家做鏡子
the royal mirror-maker.
他不讓約瑟夫去上學
He prevented Joseph from going to school.
而是白天讓約瑟夫在玻璃作坊做苦力
Instead, Joseph labored in the glass-making workshop by day,
晚上去他家裏做家務
and tended to the master's household chores by night.
快點  白癡
Hurry up, stupid!
記住 不許讀書
And remember, no reading.
約瑟夫終於解脫了
Until Joseph got his big break.
維塞伯格的房子塌了
Weichselberger's house collapsed.
馬克西米利安 巴伐利亞未來的國王
Maximilian, the future king of Bavaria,
急忙來到災難現場
hurried to the scene of the calamity
向災民伸出援手
to see if he could help.
馬克西米利安出了名的關心他的臣民
Maximilian was known for taking an interest in his subjects,
這在當年並不尋常
which was highly unusual for its time.
在巴伐利亞未來國王的關懷下
In attracting the concern of the future king of Bavaria,
年輕的約瑟夫·夫瑯和費
young Joseph Fraunhofer
他的未來從此發生了變化
found an aperture into a different universe.
而且不僅是他個人
And not just for himself.
馬克西米利亞王子資助約瑟夫
Prince Maximilian gave Joseph money
並讓他的高級顧問
and asked his privy councilor
向這孩子提供更多的幫助
to provide further help to the boy,
提供所需的一切
should it be needed.
維塞伯格還在剝削他
Weichselberger continued to exploit him
不讓他去學校
and prevent him from attending school.
但是在王子顧問的干預下
But the prince's councilor intervened,
約瑟夫進入了光學學院
offering Joseph a position at the Optical Institute.
這小小的善舉帶來了非常豐厚的回報
This small gesture of kindness really paid off.
在他27歲時
By the time he was 27,
約瑟夫·夫瑯和費成為了首屈一指的設計師
Joseph Fraunhofer was the world's leading designer
從優質的鏡片
of high-quality lenses,
到望遠鏡和其他光學器材
telescopes and other optical instruments.
他的工廠位於本訥迪克特伯伊昂修道院
His firm was housed here, in the old Benediktbeuren Abbey.
在19世紀上半葉
In the early 19th century,
這可是絕密的 超級的高科技
this was top-secret, ultra-high technology.
早期的本篤會修道士們
The Benedictine monks of earlier times
都要進過保密宣誓
had taken a vow of secrecy.
這種當地的風俗
This local tradition,
加上夫瑯和費實驗室
and the ability to restrict access
嚴格的通行制度
to Fraunhofer's laboratory,
讓他可以繼續掌控
allowed him to maintain control
這些機密
of trade and state secrets.
夫瑯和費在實驗中使用棱鏡
Fraunhofer was experimenting with prisms
來尋找製作精密鏡片最佳玻璃
to find the best types of glass for precision lenses.
怎樣才能更好的觀察
How, he wondered, could he get a better look
棱鏡產生的光譜呢
at the spectrum that a prism produced?
弗雷德裏希 請把經緯儀拿來
Friedrich, bring me the theodolite, please.
在夫瑯和費安裝經緯儀的時候
Okay, while Fraunhofer sets up his theodolite--
經緯儀是某種望遠鏡
it's a kind of telescope--
我帶你看看修道院的其他地方
I want to show you something in another part of the abbey.
聲波聽上去如此動人
Sound waves are so beautiful to hear.
想像一下 會有多迷人如果我們能看到它
Imagine how beautiful they'd be to see.
你想過為什麼管風琴的音管長短不一嗎
You ever wondered why organ pipes have different lengths?
按下一個琴鍵
I press a key...
它將一股壓縮空氣
it sends compressed air
送進特定的管道
into a particular pipe,
產生聲波
producing sound waves.
如果我們可以把聲波速度降低幾百倍
If we could slow the sound waves down a few hundred times,
它看上去就是這樣的
they would look like this.
管道的長度
The length of the pipe
決定了可以容納何種長度的聲波
determines the length of the sound wave that can fit inside it.
短的管道發出短的聲波
A short pipe gives you a short sound wave.
短的聲波產生高的音調或者頻率
Short sounds waves have high pitch, or frequency.
我們把聲波停下 仔細看看
Let's stop the waves for a better look.
相鄰波之間的距離
The distance between adjacent waves
稱為 波長
is called the wavelength.
長管道發出長的聲波
A long pipe gives you a long sound wave
低音調 或者低頻率
with a low pitch, or low frequency.
布蘭詩歌 這個中世紀作品的手稿
The medieval manuscript of this music, "Carmina Burana,"
就是在這間修道院發現的
was discovered in this very abbey.
聲波無法在真空中傳遞
Sound waves can't travel through a vacuum.
他們需要傳播媒介
They need matter to ride on,
比如空氣 水 岩石的分子
like molecules of air, or water, or rock.
但光不需要
But light waves fly solo.
他們可以在太空中穿行
They can move through empty space.
速度很快
And fast--
比聲波在空氣中快100萬倍
a million times faster than sound waves in air.
我們看到的光的波長
And the wavelengths of the light we see
比聲波的要短得多
are so much shorter than sound waves.
5萬個光波
About 50,000 light waves
就這麼長
would fit right in here.
對了
Oh, yeah.
夫瑯和費
Fraunhofer.
時間正好
Just in time.
正好趕上
We didn't miss it.
就如同聲音的波長
Just as the wavelength of sound
決定我們聽到的音調
determines the pitch that we hear,
光的波長
the wavelength of light
決定了我們看到的顏色
determines the color that we see.
棱鏡是如何將顏色
But how does a prism spread out the colors
從一束日光中分開的呢
concealed in a beam of sunlight?
當光穿過空氣或太空
When light travels through air or space,
所有的顏色速度保持一致
all its colors move at the same speed.
但當它以一個角度照射到玻璃上時
But when it hits glass at an angle,
光慢下來 並改變了方向
the light slows down and changes direction.
在棱鏡內
Inside the prism,
不同的顏色以不用的速度移動
each color moves at a different speed.
在玻璃中  藍紫色
In glass, violet light,
由我們看到的最短的光波產生
which is carried by the shortest waves we see,
速度比紅光還慢
slows down more than red light,
紅光的光波最長
which has the longest waves.
速度的改變
These changes in speed
將不同顏色分開
pry the colors apart,
把他們的光波發散到
sending their waves off
稍微不同的方向
in slightly different directions.
這就是棱鏡的原理
That's how a prism works.
如果我等會情緒失控
If I seem unduly emotional about this,
都是因為約瑟夫·夫瑯和費將要做的
it's because Joseph Fraunhofer is about to do
是牛頓可以做 卻沒有做的
what Isaac Newton could've done, but didn't.
它將帶來深遠的影響
And it'll have a powerful effect
對我自身來說
on the course of my own life.
你見證的是
You are witnessing the marriage
物理學和天文學的結合
of physics and astronomy,
我研究的這個領域的誕生
the birth of my own field of science,
天體物理學
astrophysics.
記錄在光線中
Written in the light,
在那些垂直的黑線中的
in those vertical black lines...
是神秘的密碼
is secret code.
夫瑯和費看著它們 自忖道
Fraunhofer looked at them, and wondered...
為什麼
Why?
從外太空傳來的密碼
A code that comes to us from an alien universe.
這些黑色的豎線包含怎樣的信息呢
What is the message written in these dark, vertical lines?
人們花費了上百年去思考
It took a hundred years of thinking,
探詢和調查去破譯
questioning, searching to decipher it.
很妙吧
Lovely, isn't it?
為什麼
Why?
美麗的精細結構由許多層次組成
There are many layers to the fine structure of beauty...
地球的化學成分 和它的大氣層
the chemistry of the Earth and its atmosphere...
生命的進化
the evolution of life...
獨特的脈絡
Many distinct threads.
我們就在表面挑一個觀察
Let's just examine one, at the surface...
令我們驚嘆的大自然的顏色
the colors of nature that dazzle us.
到底是什麼
What's really happening?
這些紅色 藍色
How does the red, the blue...
簡直就是大自然的神奇調色盤
the astonishing palette of nature's colors...
怎麼產生的
how do they happen?
太陽發出不同長度的光波
Light waves of different lengths from the Sun
射到地球
strike the Earth.
這些花的花瓣
The petals of these particular flowers
吸收所有低能量的
absorb all the low-energy,
長的紅色光波
long red wavelengths of light.
但是花瓣反射
But the petals reflect
短的 高能量的 藍色光波
the shorter, high-energy blue wavelengths.
星光與花瓣之間的這種互動
That interaction between starlight and petal--
還有水 還有梵高
or water, or Van Gogh--
使之產生了藍色
is what makes blue.
最長的光波
The longest waves,
我們所看到的紅色
the ones we see as red,
有著最低的能量
have the lowest energy.
顏色是我們的眼睛
Color is the way our eyes perceive
分辨光波能量的方式
how energetic light waves are.
日落
A sunset...
旗幟
a flag...
情人的眼睛
the eyes of your beloved...
閃亮的新車
that shiny new car.
他們帶來的靈感
The feelings they inspire
激發你內在的某些東西
happen when something inside you
由一種特殊的變化產生
is triggered by a particular variation
光波的能量與頻率的變化
in the frequency and energy of light waves.
神秘的信息
And the secret message?
那些黑色豎線
Those black vertical lines
夫瑯和費在光譜中看到的
in Fraunhofer's spectrum?
他們怎麼產生的
What makes them?
他們產生於 某些特定顏色
They occur when the light waves
的光波被吸收時
of those particular colors are being absorbed.
那是發生在另一個層面的事情
It happens on another level of reality,
比我們身處的這個世界小的多得多
far smaller than the world we're used to operating in.
要去那裏 我們必須變得
To get there, we'll need to become
比現在小100億倍
ten billion times smaller than we are.
我們可以從這些原子中任選一個
We could pick any one of these atoms.
還是選氫原子吧
But let's go for the hydrogen atom.
氫原子是宇宙中
The hydrogen atom is the most plentiful kind
最普遍的一種
of atom in the cosmos.
最簡單的
And the simplest.
只有一個電子
It has only one electron.
只有一個質子
And only one proton.
我們進入了量子領域
We've entered the quantum realm.
這並不符合
It doesn't correspond
通常的經驗
to ordinary human experience.
常識在這裏不起作用
Common sense is no help here at all.
以氫原子的電子為例
Take the hydrogen atom's electron, for example.
在原子中 電子
In an atom, an electron
並不存在於軌道之間
doesn't exist between orbitals.
它從一個軌道消失
It disappears from one orbital
又在另一個軌道出現
and reappears in another.
就像你坐電梯從2樓去4樓
It's as if you took an elevator from the second floor to the fourth floor,
卻憑空消失
but ceased to exist in between.
還有
And another thing.
量子電梯並不會停在特定的樓層
Quantum elevators only stop at certain floors.
電子的軌道尺寸有著嚴格的限制
The sizes of the electron orbits are strictly limited,
每種元素的原子都不相同
and different for the atoms of every element.
這就是元素各不相同的原因
That's why the elements are different.
所有物質的化學屬性都由它的電子的軌道決定
The chemistry of anything is determined by its electron orbits.
將電子束縛在軌道上的力量
The force that holds an electron in orbit
和重力沒有絲毫關係
has nothing to do with gravity.
它是電氣引力
It's a force of electrical attraction.
電子沿著波浪形的圓環
The electron dances a wavy ring
環繞氫原子的原子核運行
around the central nucleus of a hydrogen atom.
從一個軌道跳到另一個軌道
And makes quantum leaps from orbit to orbit.
忽上忽下
Up or down.
軌道越大
The larger the orbit,
電子的能量越大
the greater the energy of an electron.
電子必須獲取能量才能跳躍到更大的軌道上
An electron has to get energy to leap to a larger orbit.
然後必須釋放能量才能跳回來
And it has to lose energy to jump back down.
每次向上的跳躍都是原子吸收光波的結果
Every upward leap is caused by... an atom absorbing a light wave.
我們還不知道是什麼使它向下跳躍
But we have no idea what causes the downward leaps.
我們只知道向下跳躍產生光波
What we do know that such leaps always produce a light wave
這種光波的顏色與軌道間的能量差異相吻合
whose color matches the energy difference between the orbitals.
太陽的表面輻射出所有顏色的光波
The Sun's surface radiates light waves of all colors.
如果你透過棱鏡看日光
If you look at sunlight through a prism,
你能看到它的光譜
you'll see its spectrum.
當你用望遠鏡放大光譜時
When you magnify the spectrum with a telescope,
就像約瑟夫·夫瑯和費那樣
as Joseph Fraunhofer did,
你就可以窺視
you raise the curtain
電子在原子中跳躍的真相
on the electron dance within the atom.
當電子的能量衰弱
When the energy of the electron flags,
它降到較低的軌道時
and it drops to a lower orbital,
光波逸散
the light wave it emits scatters.
大多數不會到我們這裏
Most of it doesn't reach us.
這就留下了一個黑暗的空當
That leaves a dark gap
或者說 光譜中的黑色豎線
or black vertical line in the spectrum.
這些黑線就是
These dark lines are the shadows
氫原子在太陽大氣層中造成的陰影
cast by hydrogen atoms in the atmosphere of the Sun.
鈉原子發出不同的陰影
Sodium atoms cast different shadows.
他們的電子按照不同的曲子跳舞
Their electrons dance to a different tune.
一粒鹽由鈉原子和氯原子組成
A grain of table salt is composed of sodium and chlorine atoms.
千萬億的原子瘋狂地舞動
Ten million billion of them doing their crazy dances
僅僅是在一粒鹽中
in a single grain of salt.
一個鐵原子有26個電子
And a single iron atom with 26 electrons
龐大的宛如百老匯音樂劇的製作團隊
is like a great big production number in a Broadway musical.
當你用分光儀觀察星星時
When you look at a star with a spectroscope,
在它大氣層中所有元素上都能看到黑線
you see the dark lines from all the elements in its atmosphere.
給我任意一個物體的光譜
Show me the spectrum of anything,
不論是在地球上的 還是在遙遠的星星上
whether here on Earth or from a distant star,
我都可以告訴你 它的元素構成
and I'll tell you what it's made of.
夫瑯和費線是元素的原子簽名
Fraunhofer's lines are the atomic signatures
遍佈整個宇宙
of the elements writ large across the cosmos.
如同科學歷史上的
As with every other major revelation
其他重大發現一樣  它帶來了
in the history of science, it opened the way
更新更深層次的謎團
to newer and deeper mysteries.
還有更多地
And to the revelation that there were
秘密依然藏在光線中
many more secrets hiding in the light.
當夫瑯和費把望遠鏡和棱鏡結合在一起
When Joseph Fraunhofer combined a prism with a telescope
用它們探索天空
and turned it toward the skies,
他將星星與我們之間的距離縮短了
he brought the stars much closer to us.
他39歲時
When he was only 39,
他身患重病
he contracted a fatal illness.
可能是由於早年長期曝露在
Perhaps as a result of his early and long-term exposure
製作玻璃的有毒化學物質的緣故
to the toxic chemicals of glassmaking.
你永遠不知道下一個天才在何處誕生
You never know where the next genius will come from.
不知道我們錯過了多少天才
How many of them do we leave in the rubble?
對一位孤兒的善行給王子
The prince and his kingdom were immeasurably enriched
和他的王國帶來不可計量的財富
by that act of kindness to a poor orphan.
夫瑯和費的發現將巴伐利亞
Fraunhofer's discoveries transformed Bavaria
從偏僻的鄉下變成高科技的製造中心
from a rural backwater to a technological powerhouse.
在他彌留之際  政府急切地
As he lay dying, the government was desperate
想要保留他所有的關於
to preserve every shred of his precious knowledge
高科技光學玻璃的寶貴知識
about the high technology of optical glass.
但這只能讓一個人知道
But it could only be divulged to a person
此人有著最高級別的涉密權限
with top security clearance--
鑄幣局主管
the director of the mint.
政府保留了夫瑯和費的技術
The government kept Fraunhofer's technology
用於製造完美的光學玻璃
for making perfect optical glass
一個上百年的國家機密
a State secret for another hundred years.
後來證明這給某人帶來很大的阻礙
This would prove to be a major obstacle
以後我們會提到
for someone we'll meet later in our journey.
但夫瑯和費不能容忍這樣
But Fraunhofer would allow no such secrecy
對他的科學研究保密
where his pure scientific research was concerned.
他知道科學需要開放才能昌盛
He knew that science requires openness to flourish;
我們對於自然地瞭解屬於全世界
that our understanding of nature belongs to the world.
夫瑯和費發現譜線後
As soon as Fraunhofer discovered the spectral lines,
他立即發表了所有的成果
he published everything he knew about them.
如此重要的發現帶來的影響
And the reverberations of his momentous discovery
持續至今
echo still.
他的譜線揭示了可觀測宇宙
His spectral lines revealed that the visible cosmos
是由相同的元素構成
is all made of the same elements.
行星們
The planets...
恆星們
The stars...
星系們
The galaxies...
我們  還有所有的生命體
We, ourselves, and all of life...
擁有共同的物質
The same star stuff.
他讓我們知道了
He made it possible for us to know
其他星球的大氣層中有些什麼
what's in the atmosphere of other worlds.
遠在上百萬光年外的星系中
And in galaxies millions of light-years away.
譜線不止揭示了遙遠物體的成分
Spectral lines revealed not only the composition
也揭示了他們是在靠近還是遠離我們
of far-off objects, but also their motion towards or away from us.
通過它 我們發現我們的宇宙還在擴張
Using them, we discovered that our universe is expanding.
但分光儀最偉大的作用
But perhaps the greatest revelation of spectroscopy
是發現了不可見光
is the discovery of the thing it cannot see.
暗物質的隱蔽宇宙
A hidden universe of dark matter
質量比我們熟悉的宇宙超出6倍
six times more massive than the familiar cosmos.
由某些神秘的物質組成
It's made of some mysterious substance
不會發出 反射或者吸收任何形式的光
that does not emit, reflect or absorb any kind of light.
因為它的引力我們才知道它的存在
We only know it's there because of its gravity,
它的引力吸引著星系
which pulls on all the galaxies
並為其中的恆星加速
and speeds up the visible stars within them.
我們的眼睛可以看見很多種類的光
There are many more kinds of light than our eyes can see.
認為我們的自然只有可見光
Confining our perception of nature to visible light
就如同聽的音樂
is like listening to music
只有一個八度
in only one octave.
其實還有很多很多
There are so many more.
他們僅僅是波長的區別
They differ only in wavelength,
只是範圍很大
but over a huge range.
比如 紅外線
For instance, infrared light...
威廉費歇爾發現的那種
the kind that William Herschel discovered
X光
Or X-ray light.
無線電波
Or radio light.
伽馬射線
Or in gamma-ray light.
不僅是看東西的方式不同
These are not just different ways of seeing the same thing.
不同的光
These other kinds of light
揭示出宇宙中不同的物體和現象
reveal different objects and phenomena in the cosmos.
比方說通過伽馬射線 它使我們可以
In gamma-ray light, for example, we can see mysterious explosions
不再錯過
in distant galaxies
遙遠星系的神秘爆炸
that we would otherwise miss.
通過微波 我們可以看到
And in microwave light, we can see all the way back
宇宙誕生之初的情景
to the birth of the universe.
我們只不過才剛剛開始睜開眼睛
We have only just opened our eyes.
中文翻譯：@SaltyEggPain
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息